Before we go ahead and build a content provider
you wouldn't be out of line to ask, well why.
The simplest answer is that it allows you to
share your data safely and efficiently across app boundaries by
abstracting the underlying data source, be it SQLite like
this or files or really anything else. So that other
apps can access it without really needing to understand how
you stored it. In fact, the calendar, SMS, and contacts
APIs work that way, using shared content providers.
We're going to share our weather database later, but if
you're not planning to expose your app's data, you're
probably thinking you can skip this bit, right? Well,
almost, in a lot of cases you could,
but really shouldn't. For example, in Sunshine we're using
SQ Lite. But you could be storing data in
files, dynamic run-time data or even just a different
database library. By using content providers, it's easier for
you to potentially switch out the data source and
much easier for someone other than you to manage
the UI layer code without them having to understand
the depths of your data storage implementation. On the
UI layer, it's a generic mechanism that returns cursors.
The same of those returned by SQLite databases. So,
if your data layer implementation changes, then your content provider
is effected. Still, it's just you writing the code right
now and that's a lot of boilerplate for the sake of
following a neat design pattern. Well, keep in mind that
as far as the framework is concerned, all data is handled
through content providers. So, if you want to interact with
anything outside of your app, such as sending data to a
widget or returning search results from the newer app, you'll need
a content provider for that too. In fact, that's how the
Google play store and Gmail widgets work. As well as the
ability to get search results from Google Play. Similarly, there's a bunch
of APIs designed to optimize the process of synching and querying data,
and updating UI accordingly. And all of them also expect content providers.
That includes sync adapters and cursor loaders. Which make your
app able to efficiently sync with your server, load data in
your UI layer, and which include built in content observers that
will update your UI automatically when the underlying data changes. You
could, of course, build all of that yourself but at
a certain point the advantage you gained by not writing a
content provider to begin with is lost in the process of
having to recreate all of the useful clusters that utilize it.
We'll take a look at publishing your content provider and using Lotus
to access it efficiently later in this lesson. And we'll explore sync adapters
in lesson six when we look at doing efficient background updates. But
first, Dan is going to show you how to actually build a content provider.